We will answer the common question on whether you will be covered for pre-existing conditions
In your health insurance policy or health insurance plan, also known as mediclaim
Or whether you will be covered for pre-existing diseases
Pre-existing condition or disease is the medical condition or disease existing at the time of buying the policy
Such a condition or disease isn’t covered by the health insurance policy for a certain period
A claim for such a condition or disease can’t typically be made for 2-3 years and can go up to 4 years
This gives rise to questions like when the condition would be covered
There are questions about developing the condition before buying the policy or after doing so
People want to know how companies find out about pre-existing conditions
Which conditions qualify as pre-existing conditions
Pre-existing conditions is one of the major reasons why health insurance claims get rejected
We will address these issues by answering related questions sent by viewers
Accurate disclosure of pre-existing conditions means receiving benefits right away on its absence then
You get coverage for pre-existing conditions after the completion of the exclusion period
Sayan Choudhury asks whether one needs to inform insurance company
About medical conditions 4-5 years after buying the policy
If you didn’t have pre-existing conditions when buying, you are entitled to coverage
You don’t need to update the insurer
Even if you had an existing condition then,
A period of 4-5 years is much more than a typical exclusion period 2-3 years
Existence of pre-existing conditions shouldn’t deter you from buying a health insurance policy
One hospitalisation episode can nullify all the gains made by outperforming investments
Shubham Tiwari says his father’s age is 40 years and has had epilepsy for 20 years
Can he buy health insurance?
We believe that you have a good chance of getting the health insurance cover
The insurance company may not cover a few ailments for a certain period
The insurance company can modify their response if they assess your father's condition can trigger multiple other conditions
Blind Eyed Gaming had a disease in 2016 that got cured with medicines and has resurfaced in 2021
Can an insurance claim be made?
You can make a claim just in case you bought the policy before 2016, since then it will not be a pre-existing disease
If you bought the policy after having the condition and you disclosed it, you are eligible to claim
As a rule, truthfully divulge any information about pre-existing conditions
Meenakshi Das’ father is a brain haemorrhage patient who blood clot is now normal but has other health issues
She wants to know whether her father can get a health insurance policy
Your father should be eligible for a health insurance policy with present ailments being treated as pre-existing conditions
Apart from their exclusion for 2-3 years, you may need to pay a higher premium
Althaf Allu asks how insurance companies get to know about pre-existing conditions
The claims settlement department investigates claims applications and supporting evidence
They make an estimate of eligible expenses under the health insurance policy
Amar Kumar asks whether dental illnesses are covered by health insurance policies
On average dental illnesses don't get covered by health insurance
Injuries from an accident gets covered
Take a look at health insurance policy exclusions from brochures and product details online